A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Economic Development and Administration, Problems of the Aging FA1549
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Economic Development and Administration, Problems of the Aging
1956-1964
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA1549
2.28 Cubic Feet 6 letter document containers
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation's Problems of Aging program was a concerted effort to fund grants to help older citizens in the areas of 1.) housing and living arrangements and 2.) employment and retirement problems. At the height of the program, between 1956 and 1961, the Foundation made 42 grants and appropriations over $5.6 million. The grants were made to universities, local welfare and planning groups, and national voluntary and professional organizations. The goals of the initiative were to:
1.) Strengthen local-community action through programs designed to help older people help themselves, and through demonstration projects for improved planning and use of facilities, services, and funds
2.) Improve living arrangements for older individuals
3.) Develop sound factual knowledge on which to base retirement policies and practices
4.) Improve understanding of the employment problems faced by middle-aged and older workers through basic research and expansion of counseling, retraining, and placement services
5.) Strengthen teaching on problems of aging in schools of social work and other professional schools; and improve in-service training programs in public and private social-service agencies
The program started in 1956 with an appropriation of $500,000 granted to the National Social Welfare Assembly to be used by their National Committee on the Aging (NCOA) for the next five years. With this funding, the NCOA greatly expanded its research program and shared its practical findings widely throughout the United States. In December 1959, the Board of Trustees appropriated $300,000 for a series of demonstration projects in different U.S. communities with the goal of improving the organization of local programs for older people. These demonstration projects were carried out by: the Community Chest and Council of the Greater Worcester (Mass.) Area; the Community Welfare Council of the Richmond (Calif.) Area; the Denver Metropolitan Council for Community Services; the Health and Welfare Council of Metropolitan St. Louis; Marion County (Kan.) Department of Social Welfare; Minnesota State Department of Public Welfare; and the United Community Fund of San Francisco. The program began issuing terminal grants for the program in 1961, but the Ford Foundation continued to fund research into social issues for older individuals after 1967.
Stacey Widdicombe, a Program Associate within the Ford Foundation's Economic Development and Administration division, led the Problems of the Aging program. Prior to working on the Aging initiative, he was Assistant to the Foundation's Vice President Thomas H. Carroll.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at the RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files, and officers' papers were transferred to and accessioned by the RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary. This material was transferred to the RAC in 2019 and was ingested by the RAC as part of Program Strategy records, Accession 2019:012.
Arrangement
Collection is arranged into two series:
Series 1: Subject Files - S-W
Series 2: Office Files and Background Correspondence
The original order of the material was maintained.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains correspondence, meeting materials, grant approval materials, reports, and memos related to the Ford Foundation's Problems of the Aging program within the Economic Development and Administration department. The collection primarily consists of the office files of Stacey Widdicombe, a program associate who led the Problems of the Aging program. Materials within the collection relate to the 1961 White House Conference on Aging, the Senate's Special Committee on Aging, the National Committee on Aging, research into social issues of older Americans, social security issues, economic and housing issues for older individuals, and rights of older workers.
Some materials in the collection relate to other projects within the Foundation's Economic Development and Administration program, including disarmament and grants for business education in colleges and universities.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Ford Foundation; Older people -- Economic conditions; Older people -- Home care; Older people -- Medical care; Older people -- Services for -- United States; Social work with older people
- Subject Files, 1956-1962; 1; 0.38 Cubic Feet
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence, meeting notes, reports, and articles related to the Ford Foundation's program on the Problems of Aging. From the office files of Stacey Widdecombe, Ford Foundation program associate.
  Arrangement
  Subject Files S-W organized alphabetically by name of agency, demonstration project location, committee, etc.
  - S - Correspondence, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - San Francisco, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - San Francisco Senior Center, 1957-1962 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Santa Barbara, California, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Santa Cruz, California, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Senior Citizens Opportunities, Inc., Santa Cruz California, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Senior Citizens Service Center (L.A. County Committee on Aging), 1957-1960 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Senior Citizens Association of L.A., Inc., 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Social Science Research Council, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - T - Correspondence, 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Teachers Insurance Annuity Association, 1957-1961 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Texas, 1958-1961 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Technical Training and Vocational Education, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - U - Correspondence, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Union Settlement Project - New York, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - United Auto Workers (CIO), 1958-1961 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - United Community Funds and Councils of America, Inc., 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - United Community Services of Metropolitan Detroit, 1956-1959 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Virginia, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Visiting Nurse Association (Detroit), 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - W - Correspondence, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Washington, State of, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - The Welfare Foundation of Cleveland, 1956-1958 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Welfare Planning Council Los Angeles Region, 1956-1959 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - White House Conference on Aging - Connecticut Advisory Committee, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Office Files and Background Correspondence, 1957-1964; 2; 1.9 Cubic Feet 5 letter document boxes
  Correspondence, discussion notes, meeting materials, memos, and reports primarily related to the Ford Foundation's program on the Problems of Aging. There are materials related to other projects within the Ford Foundation's Economic Development and Administration, including the economics of disarmament and grants for business schools.
  - A National Foundation Expresses its Interest in the Problems of Older People, Dr. Thomas H. Carroll, Vice President of the Ford Foundation, 1961 January 9 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    From title page: "A speech by Dr. Thomas H. Carroll, Vice President of the Ford Foundation, and President-Elect, The George Washington University, at a special meeting of the White House Conference on Aging on "Highways to Economic Security" at the Shoreham Hotel on Monday, 9 January 1961. Dr. Carroll has had officer responsibility for the Ford Foundation's program dealing with the problems and potentials of older people."
  - Interview with Foundation Staff (John Witte?) Regarding Status of Social Work as a Field, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Nieman Fellows (Harvard University) Meeting with Foundation Staff, 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Cross Reference Sheet - See Catalogued Report: A Progress Report on a Foundation Program on Problems of the Aging, 1957 August (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Interim Aging Report, 1957 February (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Notes on Gordon-Howell Report Meeting, 1958 December 13 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Aging - Mailing Lists, 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Dr. Nathan Sinai Trip/Consultant Correspondence, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - International Rescue Committee (IRC) Correspondence, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    Notes on original folder indicate there is more IRC-related correspondence in Ford Foundation Economic Development and Administration Chronological Correspondence Files. Notes also indicate this folder was saved for potential inclusion in the International Affairs Chronological Correspondence Files.
  - International Rescue Committee (IRC) Working File, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Speech File, 1957-1961 (Box 2, Folder 37-38)
    Notes for speeches, speeches on social work mailed to the Ford Foundation, speeches by Thomas Carroll, Vice President at the Ford Foundation, and Stacey Widdicombe, Program Associate at the Ford Foundation
  - Community Demonstration Projects, 1959-1963 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    Grant status reports, correspondence, recommendations, and memos
  - Economic Adjustments to Disarmament (R. Nelson) (Emile Benoit Project), 1961-1962 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Economics of Disarmament (General), 1961-1963 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Benoit, Emile, 1961-1963 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - "Housing for the Elderly" Docket Item, Executive Committee Meeting, 1961 December 7 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Board Meeting - Aging Items, 1963 June 20-21 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Emile Benoit Project - Executive Committee, 1962 May (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Community Programs Presentation Memo - Board Meeting, 1959 December 11 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    Appropriation of $300,000 for demonstration projects to develop and improve community programs for older people
  - Evaluation Project Docket Presentation - Community Demonstration - Board Meeting, 1960 December 9 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    Appropriation of $460,000 for demonstration projects to improve the planning of community facilities and program for older people
  - National Committee on the Aging Presentation (NCAO) Memo - Board Meeting, 1959 December 11 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    Appropriation of $750,000 for general support of the National Committee on the Aging for a period of 5-7 years
  - Raising Standards in Homes for the Aging - Executive Committee, 1961 March 30 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    Appropriation of $140,000 for support of efforts to raise standards of service and improve the quality of personnel in homes for the aged
  - Job Placement Services for Older Workers - Executive Committee Meeting, 1961 September 21 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    Grant of $177,000 to Washington University for a progran to improve public and private job placement services for middle-aged and older workers
  - Teaching Materials on Problems of the Aging, Council on Social Work Education - Executive Committee, 1961 March 30 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    Grant of $160,000 to the Council on Social Work Education for the development and distribution of professional teaching materials on problems of the aging
  - Board of Trustees Meeting - American Public Welfare Association (APWA) In-Service Program Item, 1963 March 23 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    Request for approval of a grant of $800,000 to the American Public Welfare Association for a six-year program to develop and demonstrate training programs for public welfare personnel dealing with elderly people
  - "Health Services for the Aged:" Docket Item - Executive Committee Meeting, 1961 December 7 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    Grant of $325,000 to the University of Rochester for a four-year experimental program to determine the cost and adequacy of health services for the aged
  - Homemaker Services, 1960-1961 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Local Welfare and Educational Budget Problems, L60-987, 1960-1961 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - "An Evaluation of Public and Private Agency Efforts in the Placement of Older Workers," University of Illinois and Washington University, 1961-1964 (Box 3, Folder 56)
    Irvin Sobel and Richard Wilcock
  - Retraining and Specialized Placement Services for the Elderly, 1960-1961 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - The Role of the Board of Directors in the Modern Corporation L61-601, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Uniform Accounting for Nonprofit Organizations L61-900, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Associated Press (Ray Henry), 1959-1961 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Chamber of Commerce of the United States, 1957-1958 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Executive Office of the President, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - Forty Plus of Washington, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - National Farmers Union, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Resources for the Future, 1957-1958 (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - United Steel Workers of America, 1959-1961 (Box 4, Folder 66)
    correspondence and newsletters regarding older workers/retirees
  - Washington - General, 1958-1961 (Box 4, Folder 67)
  - American Public Welfare Association (Correspondence), 1959-1961 (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - L61-25 - U.S.-U.K. Study of Older Worker Problems, 1961-1962 (Box 4, Folder 69)
  - Special Committee on Aging Chron File, 1962 January-March (Box 4, Folder 70)
  - Congress - Subcommittee on Problems of the Aged and Aging - Correspondence, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 71)
  - Federal Council on Aging, 1960-1961 (Box 4, Folder 72)
  - Bureau of Old-Age and Survivors Insurance District Offices (OASDI), 1957-1960 (Box 4, Folder 73)
    Includes a Report of A Study of Referral Services by Old-Age and Survivors Insurance District Offices (OASDI), Roberta E. Townsend, Department of Health, Education, and Welfare, January 1957
  - Bureau of Public Assistance, 1957-1961 (Box 4, Folder 74)
  - Center for Aging Research, 1958-1961 (Box 4, Folder 75)
  - National Institute of Mental Health, 1957-1959 (Box 4, Folder 76)
  - Federal Housing Administration, 1958-1960 (Box 4, Folder 77)
    Housing for the Elderly
  - National Institutes of Health (Other Than Mental), 1957-1961 (Box 4, Folder 78)
  - Special Staff on Aging, Department of Health, Education, and Welfare, 1959-1962 (Box 4, Folder 79)
  - Office of the Secretary, Department of Health, Education and Welfare, 1959-1961 (Box 4, Folder 80)
  - Public Health Service, 1958-1960 (Box 4, Folder 81)
  - Social Security Administration Cooperative Research and Demonstration Grant Program, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 82)
  - White House Conference on Aging - 1961, 1959-1961 (Box 4, Folder 83)
  - Ollie A. Randall - Consultant, 1962-1963 (Box 5, Folder 84)
  - Economic Development and Administration - Budget and Grant Reports, 1961-1963 (Box 5, Folder 85)
  - Stacey Widdicombe - European Trip, 1960 April-May (Box 5, Folder 86)
    Sections include: Belgium, Denmark, France, Germany, England, Italy, Miscellaneous, The Netherlands, Norway, Sweden, Switzerland
  - Program for Programs in Aging, 1960-1961 (Box 5, Folder 87)
  - Program in Aging - Descriptions of Program and Grants, 1958-1961 (Box 5, Folder 88)
  - Stacey Widdicombe to Oscar Harkavy and/or David O'Connell (Memos, Reports, Drafts, etc.), 1961 (Box 5, Folder 89)
  - Status Reports - Program in Aging, 1958-1961 (Box 5, Folder 90)
  - Travel and Study Awards, 1960-1962 (Box 5, Folder 91)
  - Stacey Widdicombe Talk, "What! Retire at 40?," at the Drug, Chemical and Allied Trades Association Annual Meeting, Bolton Landing, NY, 1959 September 18 (Box 5, Folder 92)
  - Materials for Review Committees, 1961-1962 (Box 6, Folder 93)
  - American Friends Service Committee and Quakers U.N. Program, 1959-1961 (Box 6, Folder 94)
  - Economics of Disarmament (Friends), 1958-1960 (Box 6, Folder 95)
  - Friends Committee on National Legislation, 1958-1962 (Box 6, Folder 96)